IU Oral History Archive 1991-1998
Indiana University Libraries
- Snyder, John W.May 26, 1994, 91-264; 13 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 33 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  associate dean of college of arts and sciences; history professor; vice chancellor
  Ferrell, Bob; Gooker, Frank; Stahr, Elvis; Sutton, Joe; Wells, Herman
  African American students; Ballantine Lock-In; student protests; student riots; student unrest
- Springer, George June 24, 1996, 96-018; 17 pages, 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 59 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Restricted: tapes closed
  George Springer, born in 1924, was a professor in Indiana University's departments of mathematics and computer science from 1964 to 1996. He describes courses he taught and developed, his own education, and the types of students he has encountered at Indiana University. He also describes Indiana University's Groups Student Support Services program, a program to help prepare first-generation college students.
  Indiana University Groups Student Support Services; National Science Foundation
  computer science professor; mathematics professor
  computer programming language; computer science; distance education; honors program; mathematics; Scheme and the Art of Programming; teacher education
- Stein, Stephen J. March 14, 1997, 96-036; 54 pages; 3 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 2 hours, 28 minutes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Stephen J. Stein, born in 1940, was Chancellor's Professor of Religious Studies at Indiana University. He also served as chair of the American Studies department at Indiana University.
  American Studies Program; Concordia Seminary; Indiana University Department of Religious Studies; Lutheran Church-Missouri Synod; Yale University
  American studies professor; religious studies professor
  Ahlstrom, Sydney; Brown, Joseph; Edwards, Jonathan; May, Bill; Sampley, Paul; Stein, Frederick Carl; Stein, Irene Kroggel
  Bloomington, Indiana; New Haven, Connecticut
  Indiana University Religious Studies Program; The Power of Positive Thinking
- Stitle, Stephen A. April 15, 1994, 91-247; 9 pages; 1 tape, 21 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1945, Stephen Stitle is a 1967 Indiana University alumnus who went on to earn his law degree from the Indiana University School of Law in Indianapolis in 1970. In this interview, he recalls his days as a student at the university, including his membership in the fraternity, Sigma Alpha Epsilon, and the influence of the Vietnam War. Later in his life, Stitle became more actively involved with the Indiana University Foundation. In addition, he expresses his beliefs and fears about the funding of the university in the future.
  Indiana University Foundation; Sigma Alpha Epsilon
  university funding; Vietnam War
- Stoner, Richard B. July 3, 1992, 91-123; 30 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 76 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on May 15, 1920, Richard "Dick" Stoner is a 1940 Indiana University alumnus who went on to complete his law degree at Harvard Law School in 1947 and spent four years in United States military service during World War II. He discusses his memories of his years as a student including involvement in the Arbutus where he met his future wife. Stoner discusses the impact of World War II on Indiana University, and his eventual return to Indiana and active involvement with the university. He has been active in the Indiana University Foundation and served on the Indiana University board of trustees for twenty years, from 1972 to 1992. He speaks of Herman B Wells, the importance of the Herman B Wells Scholars Program, the question of funding for the university, and the changes the campus has undergone.
  board of trustees; Indiana University Foundation
  Arbutus; campus changes; fundraising; Herman B Wells Scholars Program; university funding; World War II
- Strauss, Jerome July 2, 1992, 91-119; 19 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 65 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on November 7, 1934, Jerome Strauss is a 1956 Indiana University alumnus who went on to earn his law degree from the New York University School of Law. Extensively involved in campus politics and student government, Strauss was first elected to the student senate and then to the position of student body president. He speaks of his experiences as a student, including anti-Semitism, upon citing his desire for the nomination for the student body presidency. In addition, he remarks on the McCarthy era and the impact of the anti-McCarthy Green Feathers group on Indiana University. One of the biggest influences on Strauss at Indiana University was Henry H.H. Remak.
  Green Feathers; New York University School of Law
  Remak, Henry H.H.
  anti-Semitism; campus politics; McCarthyism; student government
- Swedeen, Ann Whitlock May 20, 1994, 91-259; 12 pages; 1 tape, 37 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1944, Ann W. Swedeen attended Indiana University from 1964 through 1971 earning both her undergraduate and graduate degrees. Swedeen pursued a course of study involving methods of team-based teaching of the arts, and she had a strong background in music. She went on to earn another master's degree and her doctorate from Ball State in educational administration. Later in her career, Swedeen became a member of the Indiana University board of trustees and the Indiana University Foundation Board. In addition, she was active in the Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges, or the AGB. In this interview, Swedeen discusses the Indiana University School of Music, the impact of the Vietnam War on the university, and the university campus.
  Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges; Ball Corporation; Ball State University; board of trustees; Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University School of Music
  campus changes; Vietnam War
- Talbot, Sue H. April 9, 1992, 91-092; 26 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips; 72 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1938, Sue H. Talbot began attending Indiana University in 1956 and over the course of a few decades, she completed her doctoral degree. During this interval, she was a classroom teacher, a supervisor of education students at Indiana University, and worked for the state of Indiana in the area of education policy and reform. In this interview, Talbot discusses educational methods, a teacher strike in 1978, Weekenders teaching courses offered through Indiana University, and the A+ Program through the state of Indiana. She also speaks of the Japanese education system as compared to the system in place in the United States. In addition, Talbot discusses her active involvement in the education alumni association and her presidency of the Indiana University alumni association.
  Indiana University Alumni Association; School of Education Alumni Association
  A+ Program; educational methods; Indiana education reform; Japanese education; teacher strikes; weekenders teaching courses
- Tardy, Jerry March 11, 1992, 91-085; 21 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on April 13, 1939, Jerry Tardy came to Indiana University as an undergraduate student in 1957 and ended up staying on as an employee for the majority of his career. In 1971, he became the student foundation director and a few years later he rose to the position of director of the alumni association. In this interview, Tardy discusses the activities of the alumni association, Hoosiers for Higher Education, and the Indiana University Foundation, especially in the face of budgetary constraints of the past few decades. He also speaks of the Little 500 and the making of Breaking Away, a movie about the Little 500. Tardy describes his relationships with Bob Knight, John Ryan, Joseph Sutton, Elvis J. Stahr, Thomas Ehrlich, Bill Armstrong, and others.
  Hoosiers for Higher Education; Indiana University Alumni Association; Indiana University Foundation
  Armstrong, William; Blase, David; Ehrlich, Thomas; Knight, Bob; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee
  alumni center; Breaking Away; Little 500; university budget
- Thompson, Hugh Lee April 20, 1994, 91-250; 10 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 30 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Hugh Thompson describes his tenure as chancellor of the Indiana University campus in Kokomo. He describes the campus's relationship with Indiana University, Purdue University, the city of Kokomo, and surrounding communities. Thompson also details his other positions at small campuses in Michigan. Thompson was born 1934 in West Virginia.
  Baldwin-Wallace College; Detroit Institute of Technology; General Motors Corporation; Indiana University Kokomo; Ivy Tech State College; Purdue University; Sienna Heights College; Washburn University; Wayne State University
  Kansas; Kokomo, Indiana
  community college; Indiana University regional campuses
- Tobias, Randall L. June 23, 1994, 91-276; 16 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 52 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Randall Lee Tobias was born in Lafayette, Indiana, in 1942, and grew up in Remington, Indiana. He discusses the history of his family in Indiana and his student days at Indiana University from 1960 to 1964. He talks about his post-graduate work with the Indiana University Foundation and compares his student days in Bloomington with the situation there in the mid-nineteen nineties.
  Army ROTC; AT&T; Eli Lilly and Company; Indiana Bell; Indiana University Foundation
  Tobias
  miller; pharmaceutical salesperson
  Gilliat, Neal; Hewett, Charles Mason; Pinnell, George; Stahr, Elvis J.; Tobias, David; Wells, Herman B
  classroom technology; grain mill; health care; John F. Kennedy assassination; lumber mill; student life; university funding; Vietnam War
- Van Tassel, Charles J., Jr. May 19, 1992, 91-113; 17 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 46 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on April 1, 1922, Charles Van Tassel earned his medical degree from the Indiana University School of Medicine in Bloomington in 1946. In this interview, he recalls his years as a student at Indiana University, the impact of World War II on the university, and the changes the campus has undergone in the intervening years. Van Tassel speaks of his continuing involvement with Indiana University including his active participation in the varsity club and the Indiana University Foundation Board, and his interest in university athletics. In addition, he discusses the Twelfth Man Club, the problems posed by funding, and the School of Medicine in Bloomington.
  Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University School of Medicine; Twelfth Man Club
  campus changes; Indiana University athletics; university funding; varsity club; World War II
- Wahl, Cecilia Hendricks April 23, 1996, 96-008; 32 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Cecilia Hendricks Wahl, a 1938 Indiana University alumnus, returned to Bloomington in 1953 when she and her husband became employees of the university. In this interview, Wahl describes her coming of age in the town of Bloomington, her mother and aunt's faculty positions at the university, her undergraduate years, and interest and involvement in the Department of Speech, specifically the theater aspect of this department. She speaks of the impact of the Great Depression and World War II on her life and her jobs, including radio station manager and secretary to the Indiana University board of trustees. In addition, Wahl recalls her participation in the Association of Women Students, or AWS, and, later in life, the Bloomington Hospital, and the Annuitants. She speaks of the changes manifested by fraternities and sororities over the years and the rapid changes of the turbulent sixties. Finally, she fondly recalls members of the Indiana University Department of Speech, including Lee Norvelle and Bill Kinzer.
  Association of Women Students; Bloomington Hospital; board of trustees; Indiana University Department of Speech Communication
  McGreevey
  Kinzer, Bill; Norvelle, Lee
  female faculty; fraternities; Great Depression; nineteen sixties; radio programs; sororities; World War II
- Walda, John D. December 17, 1993, 91-231; 16 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 31 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1950, John Walda is a 1972 Indiana University alumnus who went on to receive his graduate degree from the Indiana University School of Law in 1975. Very involved in student activities, Walda was president of his undergraduate class for two years and an active participator in student protests against the Vietnam War. Walda speaks of the anti-war climate on campus during the early nineteen seventies and the unrest and protests generated by tuition hikes and the Civil Rights Movement, including the Ballantine Lock-In and the effects of the Kent State shootings. He also speaks of the financial problems Indiana University is facing, his participation on the board of trustees, and the status and growth of the IUPUI campus.
  board of trustees; IUPUI
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Willbern, York
  1970 Kent State University Riot; Ballantine Lock-In; minority students; student protests; university funding; Vietnam War
- Watanabe, August M. May 6, 1994, 91-251; 17 pages; 1 tape, 48 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on August 17, 1941, August Watanabe received his degree from the Indiana University School of Medicine in Indianapolis in 1967 and went on to work at the Indiana University Medical Center, first as a resident and then as a faculty member in the nineteen seventies. From 1983 through 1990, Watanabe served as the chairman of the Department of Medicine in Indianapolis. In addition, he was a member of the board of the Indiana University Foundation. In this interview, Watanabe discusses his medical training, advances in the field of medicine, the IUPUI campus, and his roles as student, professor, and administrator.
  Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University School of Medicine; IUPUI
  medical professor; physician; university administrator
  IUPUI campus; medical advances; medical education
- Waters, Lawrence Leslie June 1, 1994, 91-267; 29 pages; 2 tapes, 75 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1913, Lawrence Leslie Waters joined the faculty of Indiana University in the School of Business in 1948 and served as a professor until 1979. Throughout this period, Waters also continued to play an active role in the world of business and he gave innumerable talks throughout the world, as well as writing many articles. In this interview, he speaks of the effects of the Great Depression, stories of his former students, the McCarthy era, the teaching versus research debate, and some of the major events of his long and successful career as a businessman and as a professor. In addition, Waters discusses the Indiana University School of Business and his role in the development of several organizations, including the Mid-West Business Administration Association, or the MWBA.
  Indiana University School of Business; Mid-West Business Administration Association
  Tunisia
  Great Depression; McCarthyism; teaching vs. research debate
- Weigand, James September 10, 1996, 96-023; 34 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on February 17, 1928, James Weigand came to Indiana University in 1962 to complete his doctoral degree in the area of science education. After earning his Ph.D., he joined the faculty and became chair of the fledgling and developing Department of Science Education in 1965. In this interview, Weigand discusses the development of the field and department of science education, his education philosophy, dress codes, and the teaching versus research debate. In addition, he recalls the racism, integration, and African-American doctoral students of the past few decades. Weigand also discusses Herman B Wells and relates some stories about the former president.
  Human Relations Committee; Illinois State Department of Education; VISTA
  science education professor
  Brown, Stan; Wells, Herman B
  African-American students; dress code; education philosophy; integration; racism; science education program; teaching vs. research debate
- Welch, Dewey June 16, 1994, 91-272; 17 pages; 1 tape, 54 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on February 27, 1928, Dewey Welch is a 1952 Indiana University alumnus. In this interview, he discusses his experiences as an undergraduate student during the late nineteen forties and early nineteen fifties. Welch speaks of his involvement in the student alumni entertainers, the development of the Little 500, and his fraternity, Sigma Nu. In addition, he reveals his admiration for and some stories about Herman B Wells. He recalls his time as a student and discusses his continuing participation in alumni affairs, including activities with the alumni association, the Indiana University Foundation, and the Wells Scholars Program. In addition, he speaks of the influence of Ed Williams and Curt Simic.
  Indiana University Alumni Association; Indiana University Foundation; Sigma Nu
  Simic, Curt; Wells, Herman B; Williams, Ed
  Little 500; Herman B Wells Scholars Program; student alumni entertainers; World War II veterans
- Whitney, Dedaimia February 27, 1996, 96-005; 34 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 105 minutes; index; Department of Computer Science Departmental Report 1994-95; Kraemer, Peter
  Dedaimia Whitney was born in Norwalk, Connecticut in 1946. She was a long-time employee of Indiana University, starting in the mid-1980s. She worked as both a clerical worker and professional staff in various departments, including German, Chemistry, and Computer Science. While working at IUB, Whitney received her MFA in Creative Writing. In this interview, Whitney talks about her experiences as a staff member, workers’ rights, affirmative action, and how she helped the Computer Science Department enter the digital age.
  Bloomingfoods; Bowes Tailoring; Clerical Workers’ Union; Communications Workers of America; Department of Chemistry; Department of Computer Science; Department of German; School of Music; Shimer College; Sunflower Bakery; University of Chicago; University of Wisconsin Madison; Whole Earth Co-Op
  Bloomington, Indiana; Madison, Wisconsin
  administrative assistant
  Coppage, Jim; Foster, Bronja; Holschuh, Albrecht; Johnson, Steve; Leivant, Daniel; Lowengrub, Morton; Prosser, Frank; Robertson, Ed; Shiner, Jack; Wise, David
  African-Americans; renovation of Lindley Hall; tenure; unionization of clerical staff
- Wells, Herman B.August 6, 1991, 91-073; 8pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 30 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Herman B Wells, born in 1902, attended Indiana University as an undergraduate. After an initial career in banking, he returned to Indiana University to serve as a professor, Dean of the Business School, and then, the University's president. Wells discusses some of the challenges he faced during his tenure, including World War 11, the Kinsey Institute, and desegregation. He also gives his opinion on the fure of IU.
  Kinsey Institute
  university president
  Hutchins, Robert; Ryan, John W.
  Kinsey ressearch; World War II
- White, KirkAugust 27, 1993, 91-201; 19 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 53 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Kirk White, born on July 10, 1960, attended Indiana University from 1980 to 1984. He served as student body president during the 1983- 1984 school year. After graduation, White accepted a position as assistant to the Vice President for University Relations, later accepting a position with Hoosiers for Higher Education. In this interview, White discusses changes on campus during the 1980s, his time in student government, and his time on the Bloomington City Council.
  Boy Scouts of America; Hoosiers for Higher Education; Indiana State University; National Guard
  Crawfordsville, Indiana
  administrative assistant; assistant director of communications; city council
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Kuntz, Ed; Ratliff, Willie; Shepard, Randall
  alcohol; conservatism; marijuana; student attitudes; student government
- Wilcox, Howard S. "Howdy" June 15, 1991, 91-069; 20 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 45 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on February 3, 1920, Howard S. "Howdy" Wilcox came to Indiana University as an undergraduate in 1938. After receiving his undergraduate degree, he served in the United States army until 1947. Wilcox opened his own public relations firm and was contacted by Indiana University in this capacity. His connections with Indiana University became increasingly tight as he became the executive director of the Indiana University Foundation and a long-standing member of the Indiana University board of trustees. In addition, Wilcox had the brainchild that resulted in the creation of the Little 500 and the scholarships it funds. He also speaks of his student days including his involvement with the Alpha Tau Omega fraternity and the Sphinx Club. Wilcox discusses his association with many influential figures including Herman B Wells, Elvis J. Stahr, Joseph Sutton, E. Ross Bartley, and Colonel Raymond L. Shoemaker.
  Alpha Tau Omega; board of trustees; Indiana University Foundation; IUPUI; Sphinx Club; student foundation
  Bartley, E. Ross; Gildea, Bob; Ryan, John W.; Shoemaker, Raymond L.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B
  Indiana University regional campuses; Little 500; public relations; university growth
- Willbern, York Y. May 11, 1994, 91-253; 25 pages; 2 tapes, 78 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1915, York Willbern joined the Indiana University faculty as a full professor in the department of political science in 1957. In this interview, he discusses his years at Indiana University, the administration under different Indiana University presidencies, and the impact of different phenomena on education in general and Indiana University specifically. These phenomena include World War II and the Cold War. Willbern also speaks of some of the controversies he has experienced at the university such as those involving faculty tenure, teaching versus research, and the regional campus system. In addition, he discusses the creation of the School of Public and Environmental Affairs, or SPEA, his involvement with it, and the IUPUI campus.
  Indiana University Faculty Council; IUPUI; School of Public and Environmental Affairs
  Johnson, Lyndon Baines; Ryan, John W.; Sutton, Joseph Lee
  Cold War; faculty tenure; Indiana University regional campuses; teaching vs. research debate; World War II
- Williams, Edgar G. April 24, 1992, 91-097; 21 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 66 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1922, Edgar Williams came to Indiana University in 1947, completed his master's degree through the Department of Management in 1948, and subsequently joined the Indiana University faculty. Thus began a career that spanned forty-five years at Indiana University and included both academic duties and administrative duties, including teaching, and serving as the vice president for administration and the assistant director of the athletic department, among many other positions. Williams discusses the influx of veterans into Indiana University after World War II, the development of the Indiana University regional campuses, the status of IUPUI, the university faculty, and the financial and/or budgetary problems the university is experiencing. In addition, he speaks of the administrations of different Indiana University presidents from Herman B Wells to Thomas Ehrlich.
  Indiana University Department of Management; IUPUI
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B
  Indiana University regional campuses; university funding; World War II veterans
- Wilson, Douglas M. November 9, 1993, 91-214; 17 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 45 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean